<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Abraham's faith stated and applied a sermon preached February 16, 1695/6 / by Geo. Duncumb ...</title>
            <author>Duncumb, George, 1661 or 2-1743.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36887</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2609</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14747</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13142607</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13142607</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98009</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36887)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98009)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 415:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Abraham's faith stated and applied a sermon preached February 16, 1695/6 / by Geo. Duncumb ...</title>
                  <author>Duncumb, George, 1661 or 2-1743.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tim. Goodwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata on p. 24.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  James II, 23 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98009:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98009:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Abraham<hi>'s Faith Stated and Applied.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED <hi>FEBRUARY</hi> 16. 1695/6.</p>
            <p>By <hi>GEO. DUNCUMB,</hi> M. A. Rector of <hi>Albury</hi> in <hi>Surrey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Tim. Goodwin</hi> at the <hi>Queens-Head</hi> againſt St. <hi>Dunſtan</hi>'s Church in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> MDCXCVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:98009:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98009:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS PARISHIONERS, THE Inhabitants of <hi>ALBURY.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Beloved,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF one may make a Judgment of Mens Principles and Opinions by their moſt uſual Practices, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more apparent than that the generality of Chriſtians are perſuaded, That a Right Faith will Atone for an Irregular Practice; for otherwiſe 'tis hardly poſſible that Perſons who are Orthodox in their <hi>Creed,</hi> ſhould ſo eaſily ſeparate the <hi>Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> from it. Wherefore that you may not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded and fatally miſ-led by any ſuch falſe Notion, which makes our Faith a matter of Speculation; I do earneſtly recommend the following Diſcourſe to your Serious Peruſal, in hopes that by God's Bleſſing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companying it, it may prove a means to convince you effectually what little Reaſon there is to boaſt of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>Abraham</hi> for your Father, by living under the Profeſſion of a moſt Holy Faith; unleſs you likewiſe approve your ſelves his faithful Children, by leading a Godly, Righteous, and a Sober Life. This is my
<pb facs="tcp:98009:3"/>Aim; and if I may but be ſo happy as to ſucceed in it, I ſhall not matter what Strangers ſay of it in paſſing any uncharitable Cenſure on it. The Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation indeed is ſomewhat unuſual; for though what you lately heard from the Pulpit comes now from the Preſs, 'tis altogether a Voluntier. If this render it contemptible to other <hi>Readers,</hi> as proceeding from an overweening Opinion of a plain <hi>Sermon,</hi> it ought not to be the leſs acceptable to <hi>You</hi> for being a Freewill-Offering humbly preſented and put into your Hands by</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your faithful Miniſter,</hi> Geo. Duncumb.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98009:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JAM. II. 23.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>And the Scripture was fulfilled, which ſaith, Abraham believed God, and it was imputed to him for righteouſneſs: And he was called the friend of God.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S very Excellent Things are ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of Faith, and many Noble Acts have been done by it; ſo there is none in whom this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving-grace was more eminent than the perſon Characterized in my Text, even <hi>Abraham,</hi> who has the high Honour to be Intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>The Friend of God:</hi> And ſince he ſeems to be ſet forth as a Pattern and Precedent for our imitation, I ſhall,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Enquire what kind of Faith or Belief <hi>Abraham</hi>'s was. And,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Shew particularly what ours muſt be in order to be juſtified.</p>
            <p>Tho' probably the Scripture here referred to, may principally reſpect the Special <hi>Promiſe</hi> of God made unto <hi>Abraham</hi> touching a numerous Iſſue when ſtricken in Years; according as it is written in <hi>Gen.</hi> 15. where, upon this aſſurance
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98009:4"/>when <hi>Sarah</hi> his Wife was naturally paſt Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing, it is ſaid (<hi>v.</hi> 6.) <hi>That he believed in the Lord, and he counted it to him for righteouſneſs:</hi> I ſay, tho' <hi>Abraham's</hi> thus <hi>believing in hope againſt hope,</hi> may be reckon'd or counted the ground of his juſtification; yet is it not ſufficient to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the confidence of ſuch preſumptuous Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers as rely upon a ſpeculative Faith, expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be juſtified and ſaved by it. For this paſſage is not to be conſider'd ſingly and alone, but muſt be taken in conjunction with an ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent and a ſubſequent Act, with what went before it, and what follow'd after it; whereby <hi>Abraham</hi> gave full proof of his Faith's being no leſs <hi>Obediential</hi> than <hi>Fiducial;</hi> I mean no leſs for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to obſerve God's Precepts, than to depend on his Promiſes.</p>
            <p>You muſt note then, that beſides God's know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſincerity and ſtedfaſtneſs of <hi>Abraham's</hi> Faith at the time when he counted it to him for righteouſneſs, upon his not ſtaggering at the ſtrange Promiſe through Unbelief, He had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready experienc'd it; God had long before made trial of it by a Command of ſome difficulty, even that of leaving his Native Countrey, and going into a ſtrange Land, with which he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied without the leaſt heſitancy or reluctance; he did not hang back and object its being a hard
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98009:4"/>caſe to quit a certainty for an uncertainty; but made haſte and delayed not to fulfil the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment of his God; not ſcrupling to part with his preſent poſſeſſions, in conſidence of God's proviſion; he readily forſook his Kindred and his Father's Houſe, thereby approving him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>the friend of God,</hi> under whoſe conduct he took his journey, and followed, not knowing whither he ſhould be led, as we read in <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>This was ſuch a ſignal inſtance of his reſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Divine Will in an intire dependance upon God, that the Inſpired Apoſtle ranks it amongſt the moſt worthy fruits of a true Faith, ſaying (<hi>Heb.</hi> 11.8.) <hi>By faith Abraham when he was called to go into a place which he ſhould after receive for an inheritance,</hi> obey'd; <hi>and he went out, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whither he went.</hi> That is, he believed God, that he would be as good as his word, and in conſequence of ſuch belief, was not diſobedient to the heavenly Voice; but did as he was bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and repaired to the place appointed, tho' he had no knowledge of it; no Kindred or Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance in it.</p>
            <p>After he had long dwelt; or rather ſojourn'd here in the Land of Promiſe as in a ſtrange Country, <hi>the word of the Lord came unto him in a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſaying,</hi> (Gen. 15.1.) <hi>Fear not, Abraham: I am thy ſhield, and thy exceeding great reward;</hi> which is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98009:5"/>as if he ſhould have ſaid, Let nothing daunt or diſcourage thee, foraſmuch as I will ſtill ſtand by thee, I will never leave thee nor forſake thee; but will ſurely defend thee, and always plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully provide for thee. <hi>Abraham</hi> it ſeems had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready more wealth than he well knew what to do with, having no Son to inherit it: So that a Child was the only Bleſſing that he wanted; and therefore he takes this occaſion (not out of any diffidence, but from a longing deſire to ſee the accompliſhment) I ſay, he takes this occaſion with humble confidence to put God in mind of a former Promiſe thitherto expected by his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, even that of giving him a Son: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon this Ancient promiſe was graciouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed; and notwithſtanding <hi>Ahraham</hi> was now grown old, and his Wife both barren, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo paſt the Age of Child-bearing; yet, being not weak in Faith, he conſider'd not his own Body now dead, when he was about an Hundred years old, neither the deadneſs of <hi>Sarah</hi>'s Womb; but, knowing him to be faithful that promiſed, and able alſo to perform it, <hi>he believed God, and it was imputed</hi> [or accounted] <hi>unto him for righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not that we are to look upon this ſingle act to be in it ſelf the ſole ground of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; for unleſs he had juſtified this his profeſſed Faith by a ſuitable action in time of trial, we
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98009:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>have no reaſon to think he would have been ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by himſelf. Had he refuſed to obey the Special Command of God, requiring him <hi>to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice his Son, his only Son Iſaac;</hi> his bare belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Promiſe could never have been impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him for righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>There was no need that God (to whom all things future are preſent, and ſo may well be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by him as tho' they were) ſhould wait the iſſue and event; and therefore he foreſeeing cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly at the time when <hi>Abraham</hi> believed the Promiſe concerning receiving a Son, that he would readily reſign him up, or frankly ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him back by making an Oblation of him whenever he ſhould call for him; I ſay, this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as perfectly known unto God <hi>then,</hi> as at any time afterwards, he might very well make the imputation beforehand.</p>
            <p>And now that God has really an Eye to this very thing in imputing righteouſneſs unto <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> is very evident from the words immediately foregoing and following my Text: So that we have an infallible Interpretation to warrant the Application; for in the Two Verſes next before the Text, we read expreſly that <hi>Abraham</hi> our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was juſtified by <hi>Works,</hi> and that particularly when he had offer'd his Son <hi>Iſaac</hi> upon the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, whereby his Faith was made perfect. Whence
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98009:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Apoſtle makes this Inference or Concluſion: <hi>And the Scripture was fulfilled, which ſaith, Abraham believed God, and it was imputed to him for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> How was the Scripture fulfilled? how did it receive its completion? By the bare believing the Promiſe? No; but by his Expreſſion of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to God's Command, in being ready to offer up his only Son.</p>
            <p>The Deſign of St. <hi>James</hi> is to prove, That Chriſtians are juſtified by <hi>Works,</hi> and not by <hi>Faith</hi> only: For which purpoſe he alledges the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Father of the Faithful, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming that he was therefore <hi>juſtified</hi> becauſe he <hi>obey'd: Ye ſee then</hi> (ſays the Apoſtle juſt after the paſſage cited in my Text) <hi>how that by Works a man is juſtified, and not by Faith only:</hi> Which is as much as to ſay, 'Tis apparent from the forementioned Example, that Obedience to God's Commands, as well as Belief of his Promiſes, muſt concur to the making any perſon accepted or approved of God.</p>
            <p>So that either the Apoſtle did not rightly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Saying of <hi>Moſes;</hi> Either he miſtook the meaning, and miſapplied it (which no good Chriſtian can ſay), or elſe it muſt be taken as you have heard it now explained; namely, in conjunction with that after-Act which God ſaw would be performed in its ſeaſon, in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per time appointed for it.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:98009:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>But becauſe it may be objected, That St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſeems to have been of another mind, and in his Relation of it to put a different, or rather a clean contrary conſtruction upon it; 'tis neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary I ſhould attempt a clear ſolution of this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty, by ſhewing their real Concord, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this appearing contradiction. The Apoſtle of the Uncircumciſion having declared in <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.28. <hi>That a man is juſtified by faith with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the deeds of the Law;</hi> he proceeds in the Fourth Chapter to illuſtrate this point at large; where at the 3d <hi>v.</hi> he cites the ſame paſſage that St. <hi>James</hi> does here in my Text, and thence argues againſt the boaſted righteouſneſs of the <hi>Jews,</hi> in obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the <hi>Moſaick</hi> Law, eſpecially the diſcrimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating parts of it, which they were wont to preſs as neceſſary to Juſtification, and ſhews that as <hi>Abraham</hi> was juſtified without them, ſo ſhall his Seed be after him: But in all this there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing inconſiſtent with St. <hi>James</hi>'s aſſertion; for St. <hi>Paul</hi> does not exclude Works, or ſuppoſe that <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Faith was not approved by them: But he only rejects thoſe Legal deeds, which the <hi>Jews</hi> obtruded and cried up for righteouſneſs; ſuch as Circumciſion, Sacrifices, the <hi>Moſaick</hi> differences of clean and unclean Meats, as alſo their ſetting up a meer human Righteouſneſs, in conſiſting in outward Acts, and the like. Theſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98009:7"/>he knew would never commend any man to God; theſe therefore he condemns, as ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeded or ſet aſide by the Goſpel: And that theſe <hi>are</hi> what he means by Works, is evident from his declaring to thoſe who laid ſo much ſtreſs upon them as to truſt wholly to them, <hi>that Abraham's righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs was imputed when uncircumciſed;</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently could not be on the account of any ſuch Works as were before ſpecified: But rather ſuch as he would have Chriſtians, or all that believe in God, charged carefully to maintain, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.8.</p>
            <p>The Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> being the Law of their Commonwealth, whoſe breaches were triable in their own Courts, the manner of the <hi>Jews</hi> was to eſteem themſelves righteous in the Eye of their Law, as the World does in caſe of other Political and State Laws, when they are not lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be brought in trouble, or indicted upon them before any of their own Tribunals: Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon meaſuring themſelves only by external Acts (which alone are cognizable in human Courts) the orderly Livers among them made no more ſcruple of aſſerting their Righteouſneſs in the Eye of their Law, than any good Subjects do in pleading their innocence as to the Laws of their reſpective Countries. As we find St. <hi>Paul</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf did in ſetting off his <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Confidences; ſaying, That <hi>touching the righteouſneſs which is in the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98009:7"/>Law he was blameleſs;</hi> that is, had done nothing that could be alledg'd againſt him before any of their Tribunals, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.6.</p>
            <p>So that upon the whole matter, when St. <hi>Paul</hi> affirms that <hi>Abraham</hi> was juſtified by <hi>Faith,</hi> and not by <hi>Works,</hi> without all peradventure he means ſuch a lively Faith as did conſtantly demonſtrate its ſincerity by ſuitable affections and actions; a Faith working by love, and ſo made accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God through Chriſt the Promiſed Seed, even without performing perfect unſinning Obedience, and without Conforming to the Rites of the <hi>Moſaick</hi> Precepts: Which are the Two things that St. <hi>Paul</hi> certainly means by <hi>Works,</hi> whereever he explodes them, or ſets up Faith in oppoſition to them, and particularly in the inſtance before us.</p>
            <p>Agreeably hereunto, it is obſervable, That when the ſame Apoſtle ſpeaks of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Faith in another Epiſtle, where he makes it his buſineſs to magnify and extol it exceedingly (and ſo can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be thought to have omitted what was moſt praiſe-worthy,) he takes no notice of his belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the <hi>Promiſe,</hi> but makes mention only of his obeying the <hi>Command;</hi> as may be ſeen in <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.17, 18. <hi>By Faith</hi> [ſaith he] <hi>Abraham, when he was tried offer'd up Iſaac: and he that had received the promiſes, offer'd up his only-begotten Son: Of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98009:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>whom it was ſaid, That in Iſaac ſhall thy ſeed be called.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Story is related more fully in <hi>Gen.</hi> 22. and the Subſtance of it is this. It ſeems ſome time after the <hi>Promiſe</hi> to <hi>Abraham</hi> was fulfilled, in that <hi>Sarah</hi> his Wife conceived and brought forth a Son, it pleaſed God (as he had purpoſed of old) to make a further trial of his Faith, ſuch as might deſerve to be a ſtanding Monument throughout all Ages to the end of the World. <hi>God ſaid unto him,</hi> (v. 2.) <hi>Take now thy Son, thine only Son Iſaac whom thou loveſt, and get thee into the land of Moriah, and offer him there for a burnt-offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon one of the mountains which I will tell thee of. Abraham</hi> did not more eaſily believe the ſtrange <hi>Promiſe,</hi> than he readily obey'd this hard <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand;</hi> for, inſtead of murmuring (like thoſe of whom we read of in <hi>Mic.</hi> 6.7.) and ſaying, <hi>Shall I give my firſt-born for my tranſgreſſion? the fruit of my Body for the ſin of my Soul?</hi> Inſtead of halting between Two Opinions, or expoſtulating, doubting, and diſputing whether he ſhould not deſtroy the <hi>Promiſe,</hi> by obeying a <hi>Command</hi> which ſeemingly put him upon cutting off the hopes of a numerous Poſterity with his own hand: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold! he preſently prepared to ſet forth upon this unwelcome Expedition, with the ſame for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs as he had done formerly when he quitted the Land of his Nativity, upon the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98009:8"/>which his Faith in God gave him of that Inheritance which he now enjoy'd, together with the Heir of Promiſe. For we read (<hi>v.</hi> 3.) That <hi>Abraham</hi> roſe up early in the Morning, and Sadled his Aſs, and took Two of his Young Men with him, and <hi>Iſaac</hi> his Son: Moreover he clave the Wood for the Burnt-Offering; and when they drew nigh unto the place of which God had told him, he laid the Burthen of Wood upon <hi>Iſaac</hi> his Son, and laid him on the Altar upon the Wood; and having ſo done, he ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed forth his Hand, and took the Knife to Slay his Son. But the Angel of the Covenant interpos'd with a Counter Injunction, and ſo ſtopt the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution; declaring that God was ſo well ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with his real Purpoſe, and holy Reſolution, as to accept the Will for the Deed. For tho' <hi>Iſaac</hi> was not actually offer'd or Slain by his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; yet ſince it was verily intended by <hi>him,</hi> who had done ſo much towards it as to make all things ready for it; who had gone ſo far in it, as to come to the very laſt act of it, <hi>Abraham</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived this Teſtimony from Heaven, (<hi>v.</hi> 12. of the forecited Chap.) <hi>Now I know that thou feareſt God, ſeeing thou haſt not witheld thy Son, thine only Son from me:</hi> Which may be Paraphraſtically expreſſed thus; Thou haſt given abundant proof of thy pious impartial regard to the Commands
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98009:9"/>of God, and ſo may'ſt fairly be diſcharged from the Obligation of proceeding any further in the proſecution of this particular Order.</p>
            <p>We are not to imagine, That <hi>Abraham</hi> was acted by any ſuch <hi>Enthuſiaſtick</hi> Principle as that which influenced thoſe who made their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren paſs through the Fire to <hi>Molech,</hi> offering their Sons and their Daughters unto Devils: He could have no other Motive or Inducement (in a Country where this piece of cruelty was never practiſed) ſave only his heart's deſire to pleaſe God, by declining no inſtance of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but endeavouring to do all that he ſhould ſay, of what kind ſoever.</p>
            <p>And here I cannot but obſerve to you, the ſeveral remarkable Circumſtances which occur in this matter, and do ſo mightily heighten or enhaunce the Worth and Excellency of that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Faith which <hi>Abraham</hi> ſhewed in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming ſuch a ſingular inſtance of Obedience; and in which you may ſee how far a true lively Faith in God will carry a good man. For here was a Command to do that with which the loſs of Money, or indeed of Life it ſelf in a good Cauſe is not to be compared; nay, <hi>that</hi> from which Nature moſt abhorr'd, and Carnal Reaſon would have diſſuaded; namely, That a man very Rich and in great Authority, who
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98009:9"/>earneſtly deſired an Heir, which was born to him, when (by the courſe of Nature) he could have no hopes of one; that ſuch a man ſhould ſo overcome his natural Affection to him (which muſt needs be exceeding great) as to forego all the mighty Expectations he had from him, and conſent, after a journey of <hi>Three</hi> days, to Slay this Son with his own hands. Surely this was one of the greateſt things that ever mere man did!</p>
            <p>If he had done it inſtantly, or in the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that he receiv'd the Command, it might have been interpreted the ſudden, precipitant, inconſiderate Act of one terrified with a Dream, or ſcared with a Viſion: But to do it ſo many days after the Command was given by Him who has undoubtedly an uncontroulable Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing Power (and conſequently a right to ſuſpend the Sixth or any other Commandment at pleaſure); I ſay, to do it upon ſuch mature deliberation, is an evident proof, or clear de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of his unreſerved Obedience, and <hi>that</hi> too proceeding from a principle of pure love to God. For he did not make haſte to Slay his Son out of any fright he was in leſt God ſhould have Slain <hi>him,</hi> or ſtript him of his Eſtate if he had diſobey'd: But took time to conſider of it, that he might ſhow to all men what we ought to do in Obedience to God, even
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98009:10"/>where there is no fear of Temporal Puniſhment, nor hope of Worldly Reward; for 'tis plain he Sacrific'd his deareſt Comfort, his greateſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light on Earth, to the <hi>Will</hi> of his Father in Heaven.</p>
            <p>Thus having given you an ample account of our Father <hi>Abraham</hi>'s <hi>Faith, which was imputed to him for righteouſneſs;</hi> and ſhewn you that the Two Apoſtles, notwithſtanding their ſeeming Differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, are at a perfect Agreement, it is now high time that I enquire into <hi>ours,</hi> and let you ſee what is required in it, in order to a Chriſtian's being juſtified by it; which was the Subject of my Second General.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. Faith being in it ſelf one part of the condition of our Happineſs, and alſo inſtrumental to work the reſt, 'tis no leſs than neceſſary to be thoroughly informed what it is, and to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand well wherein it conſiſts. For tho' it be above 1600 years ſince it was firſt preach'd, it is ſtill needful to be inculcated and explain'd, eſpecially in an Age when too many who are ſuch looſe livers as to have little or no fear of God before their Eyes, would paſs for True <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers,</hi> barely becauſe they retain ſo much of the Form of Godlineſs, as to ſtand up at the Creed, and with their Lips profeſs to believe every Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, ſaying <hi>Amen</hi> to the whole; whereas if this be all, if no more were required to conſtitute
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98009:10"/>a right Faith, than thus to believe in God the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, as the Maker, Redeemer, and Sanctifier of Mankind, the moſt diſſolute Perſon, one that is <hi>abominable, diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, and to every good work reprobate,</hi> might look to be juſtified.</p>
            <p>But the caſe is otherwiſe; every Article is to be made <hi>practical,</hi> and the Faith that juſtifies muſt influence our lives. As there is no coming to God without believing that he is, ſo no Faith can bring us to him, or give us hopes of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the promiſed Reward from him, but what is fruitful in good Works; for <hi>without holineſs no man ſhall ſee the Lord;</hi> without Holineſs no man's Faith ſhall be <hi>imputed to him for righteouſneſs.</hi> We read indeed, <hi>That the juſt ſhall live by faith:</hi> But ſtill this Faith muſt be juſtified by ſuch actions as are moſt proper and agreeable to it.</p>
            <p>Faith or Belief in general, is nothing elſe but an aſſent to ſomething credible upon the Teſtimony or Declaration of another: And the Chriſtian Faith, is our believing the Goſpel and all things therein contained concerning God, our Selves, or a Future State in another World, upon Chriſt's Authority, whom we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge to be the great Author and Finiſher of our Faith. But before this can render us ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable in God's ſight, or be available unto
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98009:11"/>Righteouſneſs, it muſt deeply impreſs us, or ſuitably affect us, by working in us ſuch godly purpoſes and practices as may juſtly be expected from perſons under ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſions. This might eaſily be evinced by an Induction of particulars, but ſince the time will not permit me to enlarge, I ſhall confine my ſelf to one or two Generals.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God who at ſundry times and in divers manners ſpake in time paſt unto the Fathers</hi> [as by Viſions, by Voices from Heaven, by the coming of his Spirit upon the Prophets, and the like], <hi>hath</hi> [ſince that] <hi>ſpoken unto us</hi> [more fully] <hi>by his Son:</hi> Who came down from Heaven to reveal his Father's Will, ſo far as we are concern'd to know it: And this Revelation is Recorded in the Goſpel, to remain as a ſtanding direction for us, in full force, or of the ſame Authority with us, as if we now heard God ſpeaking with a loud Voice out of the Clouds to us.</p>
            <p>In the Goſpel we have exceeding rich and preclous Promiſes of an ample Reverſion, we are aſſured of an Inheritance incorruptible, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled, and that fadeth not away, reſerved in Heaven as a Recompence of Reward for the Righteous, for all that ſhall live godly in Chriſt Jeſus, paſſing the time of their ſojourning here in fear, ſuch fear as is productive and perfective
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98009:11"/>of Holineſs, by cleanſing us from all filthineſs of Fleſh and Spirit.</p>
            <p>Now if we believe <hi>this</hi> as firmly as <hi>Abraham</hi> did <hi>that</hi> which was but a Type of <hi>this,</hi> it will certainly incline us to do as he did, who knew no more of <hi>Canaan</hi> than we do of Heaven; I ſay, if we be as verily perſuaded of what we <hi>read,</hi> as he was of what he <hi>heard,</hi> we cannot chuſe but expreſs the ſame care and forwardneſs to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve what is <hi>written,</hi> as he did to comply with what was <hi>ſpoken,</hi> as neceſſary to get into it, or to be duly qualified for the fruition of it. That is to ſay, We ſhall be effectually diſpoſed to live like Strangers and Pilgrims upon Earth, behaving our ſelves as it becomes thoſe who profeſs that <hi>we have no continuing City here, but are ſeeking one to come,</hi> and <hi>that</hi> with ſuch aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duous diligence as is proper to ſecure it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abraham</hi>'s ſtedfaſtly believing the <hi>Promiſe,</hi> put him upon following the <hi>Commandment</hi> of God, and ſo he came to be inſtated in the Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: In like manner our believing the <hi>Promiſe,</hi> which Chriſt has made us of entring into the Kingdom of Heaven, muſt prompt us to obey the <hi>Precepts</hi> which he has given us conducing to it, before we can be admitted to ſit down with <hi>Abraham</hi> in it. Yea, the very hardeſt of them (ſhould we be called to it) even <hi>that</hi> of forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98009:12"/>All to follow him, or for adhering to him; whether <hi>houſes, or brethren, or ſiſters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, or lands.</hi> All muſt be left for Chriſt's ſake, if we mean to inherit Everlaſting Life, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.29. That is, We muſt abandon our Poſſeſſions and near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Relations, when they can be no longer enjoyed with a good Conſcience; we muſt chuſe rather to part with <hi>them,</hi> than to depart from any Article of Faith, any Eſſential Point of Chriſtian Doctrine, as an irrefragable proof or ſure token of our loving, fearing, and truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in God above all things. And that this is not a Precept of Perfection, but of neceſſary Obligation, our Saviour himſelf has clearly determined, or poſitively declared, ſaying, (Luk. 14.26.) <hi>If any man come to me, and hate not his father and mother, wife and children, bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and ſiſters, yea, and his own life alſo, he cannot be my diſciple.</hi> Which is as if he ſhould have ſpoken thus, In caſe any man that is liſted under my Banner, be not ſo diſentangled from the Affairs of this World, as to prefer me and my ſervice before all ſecular Intereſts whatſoever, he is not meet to be partaker of the Inheritance with the Saints in Light here, or Glory hereafter.</p>
            <p>If this ſeem very difficult, or be thought
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98009:12"/>above our ability, let us remember, That <hi>all things are poſſible to him that believeth,</hi> and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is too hard for a Faith which <hi>looks at the things which are not ſeen and are Eternal.</hi> You have heard of the Faith of <hi>Abraham,</hi> or his believing God, and how that in Vertue of that belief, at God's Command he left his Country, his Kindred, and his Father's Houſe, Travelling (though he knew neither the place nor the way to it) in ſearch of that Seat which God had choſen for him. Wherefore ſince <hi>we know that when our earthly houſe of this tabernacle is diſſolved, we have a building of God, an houſe not made with hands, eternat in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens,</hi> methinks we ſhould never ſcruple the utmoſt pains, nor decline any hardſhips in ſtriving for it; it being more eaſy to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome than to overlook the greateſt difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that can occur in the paſſage, from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viting, the raviſhing tranſporting Proſpect of that proviſion which Chriſt has made for us in his Father's Houſe, where there are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Manſions, and thoſe too ſuch as will continue for ever.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, To diſſipate our fears, and animate our hopes in the moſt perilous Times: We read expreſly, That the Church is Founded on a Rock, and are aſſured by the All-powerful
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98009:13"/>Head of it, That the Gates of Hell ſhall never prevail againſt it. Now if we hold faſt the profeſſion of our Faith without wavering, tho' black clouds and thick darkneſs ſhould be round about her; though the Heathen ſhould rage, or the Kings of the Earth take counſel toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and with one conſent be Confederate againſt her to deſtroy her, 'twill not ſo fill us with fear as to drive us to Deſpair, but we ſhall ſtill reſt ſatisfied with God's promiſe of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection; being confident that they muſt needs imagine a vain thing in conſulting to make havock, where Salvation is appointed for Walls and Bulwarks.</p>
            <p>This Faith will ſo perfectly caſt out all fear, even in the midſt of imminent dangers from the moſt furious attacks, as to enable us to ſay within our ſelves, <hi>God is in the midſt of her, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhall ſhe not be removed, God ſhall help her and that right early.</hi> Had the Church no Nurſing Father, none other to Fight for her but only God, ſurely her Sons could have no reaſon to fear the power of any Adverſaries; for ſince He and He alone, can Govern the unruly Wills and Affections of ſinful Men; ſince he has full Power inſtantly to make the Church's Enemies to be at Peace with her, or elſe to put <hi>them</hi> down that riſe up againſt her; did we but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feignedly
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98009:13"/>believe this, we ſhould not be ſo prone to crucify our ſelves with the fear of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hurt by any Perſecutions through thoſe Evils which the Malice of Men or Devils may at any time deviſe: Or put the caſe they ſhould be permitted to ride over our Heads a-while, and lay trouble upon our Loins, yet if we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve verily that he who Orders all Events, and brings good out of Evil, will cauſe the very worſt to work together for the good of his People, a lively Faith will diſpoſe us to paſs our time in reſt and quietneſs, as alſo in all our troubles and adverſities whenſoever they op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs us; to put our whole truſt and confidence in God's Mercy, abiding patiently upon him till he turn again and refreſh us, as he did <hi>David</hi> and his Choſen Generation, after he had ſhewed them great troubles. Whatever come upon us, this Faith will keep us ſtedfaſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable, make us always abound in the work of the Lord; nor ſhall we behave our ſelves frowardly in his Covenant. <hi>Our heart will not be turned back, neither will our ſteps go out of his way; no, not when he has ſmitten us in the place of Dragous, and cover'd us with the ſhadow of death;</hi> as the Royal Prophet ſpeaks in <hi>Pſalm</hi> 44.18, 19.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:98009:14"/>
            <p>So that ſhould the Sword be unſheath'd with a ſeeming Commiſſion to paſs through the Land, as in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14. Since <hi>He</hi> that ſtay'd <hi>Abraham</hi>'s hand when the knife was at <hi>Iſaac</hi>'s Throat, can with the ſame eaſe put a ſtop to the progreſs of the deſtroying Angel in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; every one that has, indeed, <hi>Abraham</hi> for his Father, will ſay with Holy <hi>Job, Though he ſlay me, yet will I put my truſt in him;</hi> or in the A poſtle's Language, <hi>I will not caſt away my confidence, which hath great recompence of reward,</hi> but will ſtill <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the keeping of my ſoul to</hi> Him <hi>in well doing, as unto a faithful Creator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If then any be apt to torment themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the time, by formidable apprehenſions of threatning Evils, they would do well to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the paſſage of our Saviour in <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.25, 26. where we read, that whilſt Chriſt was in a Ship at Sea with his Diſciples, there aroſe a great Tempeſt, which filled the Diſciples with ſo much dread, as to make them conclude they muſt needs be preſently ſwallowed up of the deep; whereupon they ran haſtily to their Lord as he lay aſleep, and awoke him, by crying out, <hi>Lord ſave us, we periſh! and he ſaid unto them, why are ye fearful, O ye of little of faith? then he aroſe and rebuked the winds and the ſea, and there was a great calm.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:98009:14"/>
            <p>Now ſince Chriſt (who is gone up on High and there inveſted with Power to ſave unto the utmoſt all that call upon him) has promiſed, ſaying, <hi>Lo, I am with you always, even to the end of the world:</hi> If we have Faith to believe it, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be wanting to make us live quiet from fear of Evil, even though the Earth be moved, and though the Hills be carried into the midſt of the Sea; though the Waters thereof rage and ſwell, and though the Mountains ſhake at the tempeſt of the ſame; for the Rivers of the flood thereof ſhall make glad the City of God, the holy place of the Tabernacle of the moſt Higheſt. If the Kingdoms be moved, Chriſt who is very high exalted, doth defend his Church, as it were, with a Shield.</p>
            <p>Thus have I done my true endeavour to make you throughly ſenſible what kind of Faith is expected from you; ſhewing plainly, how that it conſiſts not only in believing that there is a God, and that his Son Jeſus Chriſt was made manifeſt in the fleſh; for thus far the Devils themſelves went, who confeſſed, ſaying, <hi>We know thee, who thou art, even the Holy one of God.</hi> But a right Faith conſiſts in ſo firmly and unfeignedly believing the whole Will of God Revealed in the Scripture, as to act in all things according to it, and that with ſo much ſteadineſs, as never
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98009:15"/>to ſwerve from the Commandments upon any the moſt ſpecious pretext; never preſuming to ſet aſide a known Duty upon the pretence of <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> or by the plea of <hi>Providence,</hi> but (by the Example of <hi>Abraham</hi>) ſtill to do the thing which God Commands, and leave the iſſue and ſucceſs to <hi>Him;</hi> nothing doubting, but that if in all our ways we acknowledge <hi>Him</hi> by ruling our ſelves after his Word, he will ſurely bring it to paſs, effecting what is beſt; for the right hand of the Lord has the pre-eminence, and does in all places whatever he pleaſes.</p>
            <p>To Conclude then, Let us not Believe in Word, neither in Tongue, but in Deed and in Truth, Obeying from the Heart the Form of Doctrine delivered to the Saints, and walking in the ſteps of our Father <hi>Abraham;</hi> ſo ſhall we receive a Bleſſing from the Lord, and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs from the God of our Salvation, even the Lord Jeſus Chriſt:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To whom with the Father, and the Holy Ghoſt, be Glory and Honour, Thanksgiving and Power, now and for ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errors of the Preſs to be Corrected thus:</head>
            <p>PAge 5. l. 2. dele <hi>by.</hi> and l. 19. for <hi>has</hi> read <hi>had.</hi> p. 6. l. 5. for <hi>the</hi> r. <hi>his.</hi> p. 7. l. ult. del. <hi>in.</hi> p. 9. l. 18. r. <hi>Agreeable.</hi> p. 10. l. 16. or 17. del. <hi>of.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:98009:15"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
